Indiana University's University of Islamabad Project records, 1953-1974 C488
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University's University of Islamabad Project records
1953-1974
1966-1973
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University. Office of Research and Advanced Studies
C488
5.3 cubic feet 6 boxes
The University of Islamabad project focused on establishing a residential postgraduate university with an emphasis on advanced teaching and research in science and technology in Islamabad, Pakistan. This project was funded by the Ford Foundation and administered by the Office of the Dean of Research and Advanced Studies. The project began in 1966 and ended in the 1970s, upon completion of the construction of a new campus, the end of a faculty recruitment campaign, and the development of Master's and Doctorate programs in the sciences. The collection contains files related to the creation and development of the university, blueprints for new buildings, and a series of materials from similar programs used as reference for this and other international programs administered by Indiana University.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Administrative History
The University of Islamabad project focused on establishing a residential postgraduate university with an emphasis on advanced teaching and research in science and technology located in Islamabad, Pakistan. This initiative included developing academic programs for Master's and Doctorate degrees, with the intent that graduates become scholars, teachers, and researchers at universities in Pakistan. At the time, most scientists and Ph.D. degree holders obtained their degrees at Western universities and stayed in those countries to teach and conduct research. The goal of the University of Islamabad was to create a university comparable to those in the West in order to reduce Pakistan's dependence on foreign countries for advanced scientific training. Part of the project plan was to bring Pakistani scientists back to their home country to teach and do research with the promise of a high-ranking university position, competitive salary, prestige, and a professional work environment.
This project was funded by the Ford Foundation and administered by the Office of Research and Advanced Studies at Indiana University, which was headed by Lynne L. Merritt during the span of the project. Chancellor Herman B Wells, who was President of the Indiana University Foundation at this time, also took a very active role in the planning and management of this project. Wells frequently traveled to Pakistan, both for preliminary research and to monitor the project's progress. He remained in frequent correspondence with Dr. Raziuddin Siddiqi, the Vice-Chancellor of the University of Islamabad and director of the project in Pakistan, and served as the primary contact person between Indiana University and the Ford Foundation for this project.
The Ford Foundation grant began in 1966, and it is unclear when the Ford grant ran out or when Indiana University's association with the project ended. The latest record of IU's involvement comes from an order for a journal for the University of Islamabad's library dated 1974. There does not appear to be specific information about the termination date of the Ford grant or IU's departure from the project in this collection.
Indiana University's contributions to the project included the following: providing consultants for the organization and development of the University and planning of its campus, hiring visiting professors to teach short-term appointments at the University of Islamabad, recruiting Pakistani teachers residing abroad to the University, and purchasing library books, journals, and equipment. The grant also paid for visits to Western countries, such as the United States and the United Kingdom, for select Pakistani faculty and administrators to observe how several Western universities managed their institutions. Select students were also sent abroad to obtain PhDs, with the understanding that they return to Pakistan and join the faculty at the University of Islamabad.
Since Indiana University's role in the project revolved around managing the construction and staffing of the University of Islamabad, most of the work was conducted from the United States rather than Pakistan. Consultants and visiting faculty came from many universities worldwide, but largely from the United States, Canada, and several European countries. Indiana University was in charge of arranging these visits for all instructors, regardless of their country of origin. Visiting faculty and consultants from Indiana University included Vaclav Hlavaty from the Mathematics Department, Walter John (W.J.) Moore from the Chemistry Department, and F.B. Malik and Don Lichtenberg from the Physics Department. In 1968, Stanley Hagstrom from the Chemistry Department served as a consultant for the installation of computers purchased for the university and the training of staff.
This project worked to build the University of Islamabad from the ground up, including the construction of new campus buildings. In 1966, Indiana University entered into a contract agreement with the architect Edward Durell Stone to provide master drawing plans for the construction of the University of Islamabad campus. Stone was contracted to design the following buildings for the university: institutes of mathematics, physics, chemistry, biology, earth sciences, social sciences, and Islamic studies; a library and administration building; an auditorium and community center; and student hostels and staff residences. Classes began in October 1966 in rented buildings containing the institutes of physics and mathematics. Future phases of the project included plans to create an institute of economics, followed by chemistry, biology, earth sciences, and social sciences institutes. The first new buildings designed by Stone opened in 1971. The collection does not contain much information about construction post-1971, but the project was eventually completed with brand new campus buildings and academic programs in all planned fields of study. In 1976, the university's name was change to Quaid-i-Azam University, the name by which it is currently known.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into three series: Administrative files, Library, and Reference.
Scope and Content Note
The Collection consists of three series: Administrative files, Library, and Reference.
The Administrative files series (1959-1974) contains records related to the creation and development of the University of Islamabad. This series includes budget information, project reports, correspondence, information about faculty recruitment and program participants, and equipment purchases, including those for new computers for student and faculty use. Also included are Edward Durell Stone's contract and blueprints for the University of Islamabad campus. Items are arranged alphabetically by folder name.
The Library series (1967-1974) contains information about the creation and development of the University of Islamabad library. This series includes correspondence, book orders, and journal subscriptions. At the time of its construction, this library was considered the premiere library for research in the sciences in Pakistan. Items are arranged alphabetically by folder name.
The Reference series (1953-1973) contains materials about international programs sponsored by other American universities that were used as models or examples for the international programs administered by Indiana University. These materials may have been used by many of the international programs sponsored by Indiana University, and their use was not likely limited to this program. This series includes project reports, contracts, program booklets, brochures, and books. Folders are arranged alphabetically by country.
Related Material
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database: http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/archivesphotos/
This collection is one of four projects Indiana University administered in Pakistan between the 1950s and 1970s. For information about other similar projects, see the finding aids for C511, the University of Karachi Jinnah Postgraduate Medical Center Project records, C512, the University of Dacca Institute of Business Administration Project records or C513, the University of the Panjab Teacher Education Program records.
Acquisition Information
Accession 0487, 0499, 8128, 8129, 8132, 8133, 8136
Appraisal
The following materials were discarded from the collection: general project invoices, purchase forms, order forms, and requisitions; duplicates of reports and publications; blank forms; and invoices, purchase requisitions, serials claims, and missing issue lists from the University of Islamabad Library. Personal bank account deposits and statements as well as student transcripts and grades were shredded.
Education, Higher --Pakistan --Islāmābād --History --Sources.; International education.; University of Islamabad -- History -- Sources; Indiana University. Office of Research and Advanced Studies -- Archives; Indiana University. Office of Research and Advanced Studies -- Records and correspondence
- Administrative files, 1959-1974; undated
  - Absence Reports, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Budget (Box 1)
    - 1967-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
  - Computer Requisitions, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Computer Survey Report, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Computing (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
  - Contract - Edward Durell Stone, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Construction (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1971 (Box 1)
  - Consultants (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Ford Foundation, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - Ford Foundation, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - Hagstrom, Prof. Stanley, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Institute of International Education (IIE), 1966-1969 (Box 1)
    - Islam, Misbah, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Razi, Mohammad H., 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Stone, Edward Durell, 1966-1969 (Box 1)
  - Equipment (Box 1)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Faculty (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation Administrative Manual for Overseas Personnel in Pakistan, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation in Pakistan, 1959-1967 (Box 2)
  - Interviews of Pakistani Scholars Working in the U.S., 1968 (Box 2)
  - Islamabad (Box 2)
    - 1966 (Box 2)
    - 1967 (Box 2)
    - 1968, February - June (Box 2)
    - 1968, July - 1970, March (Box 2)
    - 1969 (Box 2)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Latest Plans for University of Islamabad, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Minutes of Islamabad Project Meeting, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Forms, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan Project, 1971-1974 (Box 2)
  - Pakistani scholars in the U.S., 1967 (Box 2)
  - Participants (Box 2)
    - 1967 (Box 2)
    - 1968-1970, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Requests from Ford Foundation, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Siddiqi manuscripts (Box 3)
    - Genesis and Early History of the University of Islamabad, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Policies and Procedures of a New University, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Problems of Foreign Aid and Technical Assistance for Higher Education, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Some Details About Conditions in Islamabad, undated (Box 3)
  - Travel (Box 3)
    - General, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Dr. Siddiqi's Trip to U.S., 1968 (Box 3)
    - Islamabad Personnel, 1967-1970 (Box 3)
    - Islamabad Personnel Visiting the U.S., 1969 (Box 3)
    - Teaching Personnel, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
    - Wells-Curtis Trip to Islamabad, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Wells' Trip to Pakistan, 1968 (Box 3)
  - University of Islamabad (Box 3)
    - General (Box 3)
      - 1967 (Box 3)
      - 1968, February - June (Box 3)
      - 1968, July -1970, March (Box 3)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - undated (circa 1965-1970) (Box 3)
    - Informational, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - Reports and Observations, Richard CurtisOversize, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
- Library, 1967-1974
  - Book Lists & Purchase Orders (Box 6)
    - 1967, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1967-1972 (Box 3)
  - Books (Box 3)
    - 1967 (Box 3)
    - 1968 (Box 3)
  - Journals to Be Ordered, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Library (Box 3)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - 1971-1973 (Box 3)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - Library Building and Library Operations, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Library Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 3)
  - Library Requisitions, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
- Reference, 1953-1973
  - Australian Universities Commission Reports (Box 3)
    - Oversize, 1963; 1966 (Box 6)
    - Oversize, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Brazil (Box 6)
    - Brasilia Project, 1961-1963 (Box 4)
    - Brazil Contract, 1959-1964 (Box 4)
    - Brazil ICA Contract, 1956-1961 (Box 4)
    - Brazil Program, University of Southern California, 1959-1963 (Box 4)
    - Getulio Vargas Foundation School of Business Administration of São Paulo, Michigan State University, 1958-1962 (Box 4)
    - Plano Orientador da Universidade de Brasília, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Technical Assistance in Public Administration, University of Southern California Program, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
    - University of Brazil Proposal – Robock, 1965 (Box 4)
  - China Program, University of Michigan, 1961-1963 (Box 4)
  - Costa Rica Program, Louisiana State University, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - Ethiopia Program, Oklahoma State University, circa 1962 (Box 4)
  - Indian Institute of Public Administration, 1959-1961; undated (Box 4)
  - Indonesia (Box 4)
    - Indonesia Programs, University of Kentucky, 1959-1963 (Box 4)
    - University of Kentucky and ICA, Kentucky at Bogor: Review after Years, 1959-1963 (Box 4)
  - International Development Programs, University of Minnesota, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Iran, University of Tehran Institute for Administrative Affairs, University of Southern California, 1958-1959 (Box 4)
  - Israel, Hebrew University Israel Institute of Technology, New York University, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
  - Italy, University of Bologna Program, University of California, 1953; 1957 (Box 4)
  - Pakistan (Box 4)
    - Colorado State College Project, University of Dacca, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Harvard Advisory Group, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Pakistan Book, 1957-1958 (Box 5)
    - University of Hawaii, 1963 (Box 5)
    - University of Pennsylvania, University of Karachi Institute of Public and Business Administration (Box 5)
      - 1957, undated (Box 5)
      - 1957-1960 (Box 5)
      - 1960 (Box 5)
    - University of Southern California (Box 5)
      - General, 1962-1964 (Box 5)
      - Executive Development Program, 1962 (Box 5)
      - University of Karachi Institute of Public and Business Administration (Box 5)
        - First Semi-Annual Report, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
        - Second Semi-Annual Report, 1961 (Box 5)
        - Third Semi-Annual Report, 1961-1962 (Box 5)
        - Fourth Semi-Annual Report, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Thailand, SEATO Skilled Manpower Project, University of Hawaii, 1959-1963 (Box 5)
  - Turkey, Monthly Foreign Trade Statistics, 1958 (Box 5)
  - Oversized items (Box 6)